《绿箭》前情回顾
Previously on "Arrow"...
是谁威胁的你
Who's the blackmailer?
设防          执行
他自称计算者
He calls himself the Calculator.
计算者有一切他所需要的东西
Well, Calculator now has everything he needs
■
本字幕由ZiMuZu原创翻译
最新下载请登录www.ZiMuZu.tv
来破坏整个网络
to melt the internet.
天呐  爸爸
Oh, my god. Dad?
翻译  PiPi 天青月白 补课狂魔 Silence 木浅薰
泰安娜  我得告诉你一些事
Taiana, I need to tell you something.
是我杀了你哥哥
I killed your brother.
翻译   桃子西 二号地球补课狂魔（救火）
翻译   迷失中城  快手迷失
西娅
Thea!
怎么了
What's happening?
校对   Reginamoon Z小花儿 小闪迷路过
精校   陈小圈
拉斯造成的伤口
It's the wound from Ra's.
如果她所获取的生命不用别人的生命来抵偿
If the life she owes doesn't come from taking others,
就只能用宿主的生命了
it will come from the life of the host.
时间轴风吹来的那片云
西娅求你坚持住
Thea, please don't go.
特效&后期   咖啡Lee[绿箭侠]       总监   苹果果
只有一个办法能保住她
There's only one way to prevent that.
打开微信   扫描左侧二维码
或搜索公众号:    ustvboom
了解最新影视字幕发布信息
我父亲曾告诉我有种叫圣莲的长生之药
My father once told me of an elixir known as the Lotus.
只要答应我一个条件我就免费给你
And I will freely give it to you on one condition.
我要你杀了马尔科姆·梅林
I want you to kill Malcolm Merlyn.
如果你真的关心西娅
If you cared about Thea,
你就不会因为治愈她的嗜血欲而跟我谈条件
then curing her bloodlust wouldn't come with any conditions.
西娅是我的小姑子
Thea is my sister-in-law.
你是我的丈夫
You are my husband.
我不是你的丈夫
I'm not your husband.
但是开战了就不会顾及亲情友情了
But war does not know family bonds nor friendly sentiments.
你要跟谁开战
Who are you at war with?
我刚告诉你我想让你杀了马尔科姆·梅林
I just told you I want you to kill Malcolm Merlyn.
猜猜看
Try to guess.
如果你对马尔科姆·梅林有意见
If you have a problem with Malcolm Merlyn,
自己解决
deal with it yourself.
别把我和我妹妹牵扯进来
Do not involve me or my sister.
是你把恶魔首领戒指交到马尔科姆手上的
You put the demon's head ring on Malcolm's hand.
你
You--
你无法打败他
you can't defeat him.
但你可以  你打败过
But you can. You have.
那是在我知道他是我妹妹的生父之前
And that was before I knew that he was my sister's father.
那就杀了他让他的孩子活下去
So he dies so his child might live.
你父亲不也做了类似的事情吗
Didn't your father make a similar bargain?
我很抱歉  奥利弗
I'm sorry, Oliver.
如果不是被逼无奈我不会出此下策
I would not resort to this if I had any other choice.
妮莎  我妹妹快要死了
Nyssa, my sister is dying
都是因为你父亲的所做所为
because of something that your father did.
我觉得你并非走投无路
I think you have every choice.
西娅要死了是因为他父亲的所作所为
Thea is dying because of what her father did.
我只是循着事物注定的命运而行
I am only following events to their inevitable conclusion.
绿 箭
第四季  第十三集
这感觉真奇怪
You know, it's strange,
看着自己的女儿喝咖啡
watching your baby girl drink coffee.
是  如果你过去的18年里见过你女儿
Yeah. It would probably be a little less strange
就不会感觉这么奇怪了
if you'd seen your baby girl in the last 18 years.
你说得对
You're right.
我猜现在说
I don't suppose it helps
我曾以为远离你的生活对你来说最好
if I say that I thought staying out of your life
也于事无补了
was the best thing for you.
我当时是在保护你和你妈妈
I was protecting you and your mother.
你是在保护你自己
You were protecting yourself.
你被警察通缉了
You were wanted by the police,
又不想去坐牢
and you didn't want to go to jail.
所以你就走了
That is why you stayed away.
那你知道警察为什么要抓我
And you know why the police were after me,
我犯了什么罪吗
the type of criminal I was?
妈妈没有细说
Mom never went into detail.
我猜是什么小事吧
I assume petty stuff.
因为其他事都需要太多投入
Anything else requires commitment.
我现在来了
Well, I'm here now,
我希望我们能开诚布公
and I want us to speak openly.
我会回答你所有的问题
I'll answer any questions you have.
好  我现在只有一个问题
Ok. I just have one at the moment.
为什么现在回来
Why now?
我在为一个人做事
I was doing a job for someone.
我差一点被打败  差一点
Almost got beat, almost.
我的对手技术非凡
My adversary had exceptional skills.
激发了我的好奇心
My curiosity piqued.
我做了进一步调查
I investigated further.
猜猜我发现了什么
Imagine what I discovered...
守望者
Overwatch.
再见
Bye.
再也不见
See you never.
费莉西蒂  等等
Felicity, wait.
事情不像你想得那样
It is not what you think.
我的雇主  我的工作绝不邪恶
My employer, my work is hardly diabolical.
我会把你的话转告给你威胁过的朋友
I'll be sure to tell that to my friend who you blackmailed.
用短暂的违法来解决长期的社会问题
Short-term legal mischief for long-term societal game.
你在麻省理工的黑客行动不正是这样吗
Isn't that kind of hacktivism exactly what you did at MIT?
这和你现在所做的治安维护
Is it really all that different
真的有什么不同吗
from the vigilantism you practice today?
我们是一样的  你和我
We are the same, you and I.
我很确定我没有想要杀死八千人
I am pretty sure that I didn't try to kill 8,000 people.
那只是个空口威胁  我发誓
An empty threat, I swear to you.
我知道我没这个资格
I know I have no right.
我只想要你给我一个机会
I'm asking for a chance,
向你证明我不是个坏人
a chance to prove to you that I'm not a bad guy
而且我真的不是坏人
and that I'm not a bad guy.
那是什么
What is that?
一份我这些年来的黑客工作记录
A record of some of the hacks I've done throughout the years.
我选了一些可以被新闻验证的
I've selected ones that could be verified by news accounts
这样你就知道我说的都是实话
so you know I'm telling the truth.
这对我来说很简单  费利西蒂
This is very simple for me, Felicity.
我希望能重返你的生活
I want to be back in your life.
我知道要想做到那点
I know that doing that
就需要再次赢得你的信任
will require earning your trust back.
我希望  这是
I hope this is a first step
漫长道路上的第一步
down that very long road.
现在娜莎用西娅的生命作威胁
So Nyssa's holding Thea's life hostage
要你杀死马尔科姆·梅林
until you kill Malcolm Merlyn?
如果她不是恶魔之女我才震惊呢
I would be surprised if she wasn't the daughter of the demon.
那不好笑  约翰
That's not funny, John.
确实不好笑  西娅要死了
No, it's not. Thea's dying.
她只剩下一两天的时间
She has one, maybe two days,
如果我们能救她
and if we can save her
只要杀死那个杀害我妹妹的凶手
by killing the man that killed my sister,
你还犹豫什么
then how could you even think twice about that?
我不是维护马尔科姆
I'm not gonna defend Malcolm.
他策划了你妹妹的谋杀
He orchestrated your sister's murder,
他杀了汤米
he killed Tommy.
但没有什么能改变他是西娅家人的事实
Nothing is ever gonna changed the fact that he is Thea's family.
我不知道对于我父亲你还记得多少
I don't know how much you remember of my father,
他不是个好人
but he was not a good man,
和马尔科姆·梅林同流合污
threw in with Malcolm Merlyn,
但尽管如此种种
and all of that being said,
我还是愿意不惜一切代价换他活着
there is nothing that I wouldn't do to have him back.
所以我怎么能把杀掉西娅的父亲
So you tell me how am I supposed to take that away from Thea?
但奥利弗  如果西娅死了又有什么区别
But, Oliver, what's the difference if Thea dies?
没必要走到那一步  约翰
It doesn't have to come to that, John.
还有更多的选择
There's more than one choice here.
-比如呢  -外交手段
- Like what? - Diplomacy.
娜莎想要什么
What does Nyssa want?
娜莎真正想要的是控制刺客联盟
I mean, all Nyssa really wants is control of the League,
所以我需要说服梅林把戒指交给她
So I need to convince Merlin to give her the ring,
她给我们解药  没有人需要死
she gives us the cure, and no one has to die.
劳蕾尔  你能说服娜莎接受这个提议吗
Laurel, can you convince Nyssa to go along with that?
可以  总比说服梅林来的容易
Yeah. It's easier than talking Malcolm into it.
梅林就交给我吧
Well, let me worry about Malcolm.
我不明白
I don't understand.
你为什么救了我却要杀了我哥哥
Why would you save me only to kill my brother?
他袭击了我
He attacked me.
瓦勒徳才不会那么做
Vlad would never do such a thing.
我只是自卫
I was defending myself,
我那时候也不知道他是你哥哥
and I did not know he was your brother.
知道了有什么区别吗
Would that have made a difference?
我别无选择
I didn't have a choice.
人总是有选择的
There is always a choice.
我不能让他杀了我
I couldn't just let him kill me.
我和你玩完了
I'm done with you.
泰安娜  我这里有瑞特想要的东西
Taiana, I have something that Reiter wants.
你从哪里得来的
Where did you get that?
那不重要
It doesn't matter.
我想我们可以用它来对付他
I think that we can use this against him.
我有个更好的主意
I have a better idea.
去叫瑞特
Get Reiter.
告诉他我想和他谈谈
Tell him I want to talk to him.
我这有他想要的东西
I have something that he wants.
你看我有没有理解错
Let me see if I've got this right.
现在有个我们从没听说过的神奇药剂
There's a magic potion that could cure Thea's bloodlust
能够治愈西娅的嗜血心性
that we've never heard of
但是碰巧娜莎就有
but Nyssa conveniently has.
我这些年一直没有告诉你  奥利弗
I've been holding off telling you this for years, Oliver.
你长得很帅
You're very handsome,
但真的不太聪明
not especially bright.
足够聪明去证实她的话了
Bright enough to have checked.
那东西叫做圣莲
It's called the Lotus.
塔苏·山城原来就是保护圣莲组织的一员
Tatsu Yamashiro is part of the order who guards it--or did.
他们把它给了娜莎
They gave it to Nyssa,
如果我们现在不说服她给西娅的话
and if we don't get her to give it to Thea now...
我们就会失去她
We're gonna lose her.
即使假设这种长生之药真的存在
Even assuming such an elixir existed,
假设山城小姐的组织
even assuming Miss Yamashiro's order
自愿交出它
parted with it willingly,
并且假设娜莎·厄尔·高福的话可信
even assuming Nyssa Al Ghul's words could be trusted,
那么好的
then yes.
我当然会为我的女儿做任何事
Of course I'd do anything to save my daughter,
但是这些都不是真的  奥利弗
but none of that is true, Oliver.
听着  我很欣赏你努力保持
Look. I appreciate you're trying to embrace
比较乐观的态度
a more optimistic viewpoint these days--
梅林  我们现在讨论的是你的女儿
Malcolm, we're talking about your daughter.
是的
Yes,
我需要想办法来救她
and I need to do something to save her,
而你需要停止使用娜莎·厄尔·高福的把戏
and you need to stop wasting my time
来浪费我的时间
with Nyssa Al Ghul's games.
我们在边界发现了她
We found her at the perimeter.
她声称自己是朋友
She claims to be a friend.
她说的是实话
And she speaks the truth,
至少在她亵渎了我心爱的人
At least until she defiled my beloved
还眼睁睁地看着我被关进地牢之前是这样
and stood idly by while I was left to rot in a dungeon.
退下吧
Leave us.
娜莎
Nyssa...
我的爱人现在还好吗
How is my beloved?
莎拉很好  她已经痊愈了
Sara's good. She's whole.
我觉得她现在很幸福
I think she's happy.
如果你来是为了西娅
If you're here about Thea--
娜莎  你在做什么
Nyssa, what are you doing?
保护我与生俱来的权利
Protecting my birthright.
以西娅的生命相要挟吗
By holding Thea's life hostage?
说得好像她没有射死你的妹妹一样
You say that as if she didn't fire the arrows that felled your sister.
你我都心知肚明那不是她的错
You and I both know that wasn't her doing.
没错  是马尔科姆·梅林
Yes. It was Malcolm Merlyn.
而现在他该付出代价了
And the time has come for recompense.
我永远都不会原谅梅林
I will never forgive Merlyn
做出的那些伤天害理的事情
for all the horrible things that he's done.
他杀了人
He's taken people,
杀了我身边两个非常重要的人
two very special people away from me.
难道你看不出我也想杀了他吗
Don't you think I want him dead?
那你来这做什么
Then why are you here?
因为如果你想杀了梅林
Because if you want Merlyn dead,
你就必须亲自动手
then you have to drive that sword.
如果你不能或是不想动手的话
And if you can't or if you won't,
那我们就得各退一步想出解决之策
then we'll need to negotiate a compromise.
你有什么提议
You have my attention.
奥利弗会劝梅林让位
Oliver convinces Merlyn to give up the power,
而你
And you...
你要把解药交给我们
And you give us the cure.
这条件我接受
I would accept those terms,
但梅林不会同意的
but Merlyn never will.
他的事我们来想办法
Let us worry about that.
说到"我们"  你是指我丈夫吧
And by "us," you mean my husband?
奥利弗现在正在和梅林谈
Oliver's speaking with Merlyn right now,
虽然梅林是个十恶不赦的混蛋
And Merlyn--he is a bastard,
但为了救自己女儿一命他会付出一切
but there is nothing that he wouldn't do to save his daughter.
希望如此
I hope so
因为如果他拒绝的话
because if he doesn't,
死的人就不只是西娅了
it won't just be Thea's life that is forfeit.
什么意思
What do you mean?
我们会开战
There will be war,
而你家乡的大街小巷
and the streets of your home will run red
都会被我们敌人的鲜血染红
with the blood of our enemies,
无论敌人是谁
Whomever they may be.
和梅林谈得怎么样
How'd it go with Merlyn?
最新美剧下载
www.ZiMuZu.tv
不顺利  娜莎那边呢
Not good. Nyssa?
她带了一支军队  但只要你把戒指给她
She brought an army, but if you get her the ring,
她就会合作
she'll play ball.
我们不需要伤害任何人也能解决这件事
We can get this done with no one getting hurt.
一切都好吗
Everything all right?
不  不太好
No, not really.
我是说  不是特别好
I mean, it's not great.
只是还没到
It's just not quite at the level
"我妹妹就快死了"那么糟糕
of "My sister's on her deathbed" kind of bad, so...
发生了什么
What happened?
我爸爸回来了
My dad came back.
这为什么是件坏事
And why is that a bad thing?
这件事说来话长
Well, it's an extremely long story,
不过你还记得威胁罗伊的那个黑客吗
But you remember the superhacker who blackmailed Roy?
-那是我爸爸  -什么
- Same guy. - What?
你爸爸是
Your father is...
计算者  他来了我帕尔默科技的展示会
The Calculator. He showed up at my Palmer Tech presentation.
我昨天去和他喝了杯咖啡
I had coffee with him yesterday,
他告诉了我他是计算者这个爆炸性消息
where he dropped the Calculator bomb on me.
他为什么要那么做
And why would he do that?
显然他已经知道了我的事情
Apparently now that he knows what I do,
知道了我们俩都是"治安维持者"
that we're both "vigilantes,"
我们有了共同点
We have something in common.
最烦的是我很想相信他
The sickest part is I want to believe him.
真希望我能做个什么测试
I wish there were some sort of test
来看看他到底是不是如他所说的那样
I could do that would prove that he is who he says he is.
测试是个好主意
A test is a good idea.
对你和我们的事都是好主意
It's a good idea for you and for us.
我有办法让梅林和我谈判了
I've got a way to bring Merlyn to the bargaining table.
我通常是不会被阶下囚叫来的
I'm not usually one to be summoned by my prisoners.
听说你有东西要交给我
I heard you had something for me.
泰安娜  求你了  别这么做
Taiana, please. No.
我有你想要的东西
I have something you want.
把我放出来我就交给你
Let me out of this cage, and it's yours.
把东西给我看看
Show me what you have.
真美啊
Magnificent.
我们达成协议了吗
Do we have a deal?
协议
A deal?
你误会了
You misunderstood.
无论如何它都是我的
It's mine either way.
我不能呆在这  瑞特
I cannot stay here, Reiter.
这个人杀了我哥哥
This man killed my brother.
那你就要像照顾你哥哥一样
And you will continue to care for him
继续照顾他
ss if he were your brother.
奎恩先生是我这岛上事业的一枚重要棋子
Mr. Queen is an important piece of my endeavor on this island.
你要照顾他直到他痊愈
You'll stay with him until he's well.
如果他情况恶化
If his health gets worse,
你也得跟他一起死
you'll join him in his fate.
你左侧格挡太慢了
Your left-side block is slow.
你的下一个对手可不会像我这么有耐心
your next opponent won't have my patience
也不会像我这么仁慈
or my mercy.
显然你还没搞清楚这事该如何进行
Clearly you don't understand how this is supposed to work,
我的丈夫
my husband.
你本该把魔术师带来这里
You were supposed to bring the Magician with you.
你要先向我
Well, I need something from you first--
证明你提议的真实性
proof that what you're offering is real.
拖延策略
A stalling tactic.
厄尔·萨赫尔认为我是傻瓜
Al Sa-her thinks me the fool
或者你才是傻瓜
or that you're one.
也许他不相信
Or maybe he doesn't trust the woman
想要抢走他恶魔头子戒指的女人
trying to take the demon's head ring from him.
想不通为什么
Can't imagine why.
把圣莲样本拿给我
Bring me a sample of the Lotus.
我知道你在想什么
I recognize what you are doing.
虽然我内心尊重这种想法
Part of me even respects it,
但是刺客联盟的领袖
but the leadership of the League of Assassins
悬而未决
is in the balance here.
你认为能以不流血的方法解决
It is naive to think this can be resolved
太天真了
without bloodshed.
这点量不足以永久地治愈她
This amount is not sufficient to cure her permanently,
但能证明给梅林看
only to provide the assurance Merlyn seeks.
谢谢你  娜莎
Thank you, Nyssa.
我说过  有人会死
As I said, someone is going to die.
我希望那人不是你妹妹
I pray it won't be your sister.
帮她办出院手续会困难吗
Was it difficult to get her discharged from the hospital?
不难  我跟兰博医生说过了
No. I spoke to Dr. Lamb.
他是我们家的朋友
Friend of the family.
娜莎
Nyssa...
她给了我们解药的样本作为证明
she hooked us up with a sample of the cure.
这能让西娅坚持久一点
This buys Thea some more time,
你也得到你想要的证明
and you get the proof that you need.
看看如何吧
Let's see it.
娜莎的交换条件是什么
What are Nyssa's terms?
你交出戒指
You hand over the ring,
她把剩下的灵药给我们
she gives us the rest of the elixir,
西娅就不会死
and Thea lives.
我们什么时候能见面
When can we meet?
今晚
Tonight.
劳蕾尔现在和她在一起
Laurel's with her now.
我收到你的...
Hi! I got your--
糟了
Oh, no.
糟了  你现在的样子跟方块熊先生一样
Oh, no. You have Mr. Square Bear face.
什么
What?
方块熊先生
Mr. Square Bear.
天呐  你不记得了
Oh, my God. You don't remember.
你大概四岁的时候  把它弄丢了
You lost him when you were, like, 4 years old,
你当时的样子
and you had that exact--
你当时的样子跟现在一模一样
you had that exact look on your face.
宝贝
Oh, baby.
希望没有比丢了毛绒娃娃更严重的事
Is it too much to hope that you lost a plushy toy?
没  但是年龄增长和通货膨胀
No, but adjusting for age and inflation,
也挺难受的
might be just as bad.
你要坐下来吗
You want to sit?
怎么了
What? What's up?
是爸爸
It's dad.
诺亚  他来了星城
Noah-- he's in Star City.
什么  你怎么知道
What? How do you know?
他来找我
He came to see me.
你跟他聊了吗
Did you talk to him?
聊了
Yeah.
你没事吧
Are you all right?
没事  你怎么一副他会伤害我的样子
Yeah. You sound like you think he'd hurt me or something.
没错
Yeah.
我一直在调查
I've just been doing some checking.
有没有可能
Is it possible that he's not
他已经不是我们认识的那个人
the guy we thought he was, that maybe he's better
也许他变好了
than we thought he was?
不会
No.
费利西蒂  我很想认为你父亲
Felicity, I would love to think that your father
现在出现在你的生活中
didn't show up with some ulterior motive
并不是别有用心
in your life right now,
但是这种情况我见过了很多次
but I've been where you are more times
已经多到无法想象  可结果总是一样
than I care to admit, and it always ends the same way.
你希望听到什么  他就会说些什么
He tells you exactly what you want to hear,
你会被他的话所吸引
and you get sucked in,
然后就会发现自己丢掉了工作
and the next thing you know, you have no job,
口袋空空
no money,
无法给可爱的七岁女儿
and a sweet 7-year-old daughter
买双新鞋子
who needs a new pair of shoes
无法让她去参加太空夏令营
and wants to go to space camp.
人是不会变的
People don't change,
即使你希望他们有所改变
even if you want them to.
好吧
OK.
你做得对
You're doing the right thing.
我愿意考虑奥利弗天真的计划
I'm only entertaining Oliver's naive plan
只是因为我尊重我们的婚姻
out of respect for our marriage,
但是他的希望让他对现实视而不见
but his hope blinds him to reality.
你身着战衣过来  厄尔·萨赫尔
You come dressed for battle, Al Sa-Her.
只是为了配合这个场合
Just for the occasion.
以此交换我女儿的性命
In exchange for my daughter's life.
很高兴你终于明白了
I'm glad you've finally seen reason.
可惜  我明白的只是
Sadly, the only thing I have seen
你将会很快死去
is your quick and speedy death.
马尔科姆
Malcolm!
我就知道不能相信你
I knew you couldn't be trusted.
既然知道  却毫无准备
You knew, and you didn't prepare,
你和往常一样寡不敌众  武器不足
and here you are outnumbered, outgunned,
毫无策略
out maneuvered per usual.
娜莎  不要
Nyssa, don't!
杀了他
Kill him!
我们得在他们杀掉对方前阻止他们
We need to stop them before they kill each other.
撤退
Retreat!
别让她跑了
Don't let her get away!
马尔科姆  住手
Malcolm, stop this now!
让开  奥利弗
Get out of my way, Oliver!
想想西娅
Think about Thea!
不要质疑我对我女儿的爱
Do not question my love for my daughter.
我做的一切  都是为了她
Everything I do, I do it for her.
我不会让开
I'm not moving.
非暴力不抵抗也就到此为止了
So much ‭for the Gandhi method.
考虑到那是马尔科姆  行不通才正常
Given who we're dealing with, we shouldn't be surprised.
我真不敢相信当拉斯·厄尔·高福
I can't believe that being Ra's Al Ghul
对马尔科姆来说
is more important to Malcolm
居然比他女儿的性命还重要
than saving his daughter's life.
我知道你想改变行事方式
I know that you're trying a new approach,
但是你改变了
but just because you've changed,
并不代表所有人都变了
that doesn't mean everybody else has.
我们不能眼看着联盟内战
We cannot allow a league civil war.
会牵涉太多人无辜伤亡
Too many people will be collateral damage.
就凭我们四个  绝对无法撂倒
And the 4 of us definitely can't take on
两个刺客军团
two armies of assassins.
所以擒贼先擒王
Then we take down the generals.
我们得找到妮莎和马尔科姆
We need to work on locating Nyssa and Malcolm.
但主要找妮莎
But mainly Nyssa
因为那个叫什么圣莲的解药
because she's got that whole Lotus cure thing.
两个都要找到
We find both of them.
今晚不能再有人死
No one else dies tonight.
尤其是西娅
Especially Thea.
你得吃了这个  控制高烧
You need this to keep your fever at bay.
如果再烧起来
If it comes back,
结果很不好
well, that would be very bad.
没想到你还在乎我
I'm surprised you still care.
巴伦·瑞特说得很清楚
Baron Reiter made it very clear
你死掉我会有什么下场
what happens to me if you die.
泰安娜  我理解你现在的心情
Taiana, I know what you're going through.
是那种腹部深处传来的感觉
It's this feeling in the pit of your stomach.
深深的空虚感
It's an emptiness--
不许你帮我为
Don't you dare try to help me mourn
被你杀掉的哥哥哀悼
my brother that you took from me.
请听我说
Please just listen.
你根本不懂我的感受
You know nothing about how I feel!
你这种没心没肺的人
A man with a heart as small as yours
根本不会有感情
is incapable of such things.
我父亲为了救我的命
My father sacrificed himself
牺牲了他自己
so I could survive,
为了让我弥补他的过错
so that I could right his wrong.
他吞枪自尽了
He did it by pulling out a gun
就在离我不到
and shooting himself in the head
一米的地方
not 3 feet from me.
那天之后  我又失去了
Since that day, I have lost
四个我爱的人
4 more people that I love,
我很在乎他们
that I cared so much about.
一次比一次痛苦
It never gets easier ever.
我们第一次见面
I could see it in your eyes
我就从你的眼神里看出来了
from the moment we first met.
看出我是好人吗
That I was good?
不  看出你迷失了  心碎了
No. That you were lost, shattered.
有句俄国谚语
There is a Russian saying--
破镜之锤  也能锻铁成钢
"Tot zhe molot chto drobit steklo, kuyet stal."
意思是打碎玻璃的锤头  也能锻出精钢
"The same hammer that shatters glass forges steel."
如果你想成为你父亲想让你成为的那个人
If you want to be the man that your father wishes you to be,
这就是你的机会
then this is how you'll get there.
救我们离开瑞特之手
You save us from Reiter,
但现在这个心碎的你做不到
but you cannot do that shattered.
大家说的都一样
Hey. Everyone's telling the same story--
穿黑袍的两方人对打
Guys in black robes fighting each other.
没错  刺客联盟
Yeah. League of assassins.
解决一点领导问题
They're working on some leadership issues.
但解决之前还得死
Yeah, but how many more people are gonna die
-多少人啊  -我们在想办法了
- before that happens? - Yeah. We're working on it.
你们得再快点
You got to work faster.
这只是个开始
This is just the beginning.
我觉得我们需要谈谈
I think we need to talk.
谈什么
About what?
谈最显而易见的那件事
About the elephant in the room.
要解决这件事  只有一个办法
The way this is going down, it ends one way--
解决马尔科姆·梅林
Malcolm Merlyn.
必须撂倒他  奥利弗
He has to be taken down, Oliver.
只有你成功过
You're the only man who's ever done it.
马尔科姆杀了几百人
Malcolm's killed hundreds of people.
他杀了汤米  他杀了莎拉
He killed Tommy, he killed Sara.
西娅现在命悬一线
Thea is dying right now
都是因为他挑起的事端引起的
because of events that he set in motion.
他绝对是我
I have never hated anyone
最憎恨的人
the way that I hate him.
你一直在否认  奥利弗
You've been in denial, Oliver,
你还是非常希望
holding onto hope with both hands
自己不用屈服于这种仇恨
that you don't have to give in to that hate,
被这种仇恨逼到别无选择
use that hate to do what needs to be done,
但是奥利弗  你已经别无选择了
but, Oliver, this needs to be done.
你必须杀掉马尔科姆·梅林
You have to kill Malcolm Merlyn.
很高兴你打给我
I'm glad you called.
你的资料都证实了
Well, all your files checked out,
我自己也做了些调查
and I did some additional digging myself.
你说得没错
You're right.
我们俩  确实很像
You and I, we're not all that different.
这里真的很不错
This facility is really amazing.
是的  失败多次之后
Yes. After numerous false starts
研发部终于能像
we finally got the R&D section
瑞士手表一样顺畅运作
working like a Swiss Watch.
我们大部分的前沿项目都在这一层
This floor contains most of our bleeding edge projects.
那是领先蓝牙技术3代的
That is an autonomous communications device
自主通讯设备
three generations beyond bluetooth.
外壳部分看不出接缝
But there are no seams in the casing.
是的  它是用一整块铝做成的
I know. It's built from a single piece of aluminum.
整个表面连接着电磁感应充电器
The entire surface connects to an induction charger.
你是如何让它散热的
How did you achieve the heat sink?
其实是柯蒂斯·霍特解决了这个问题
Curtis Holt achieved it actually.
他挺有才的
He's quite the genius.
别小看自己
Don't sell yourself short.
你是这方面的史蒂夫·乔布斯
You're the Steve Jobs in this equation.
谢谢你答应给我第二次机会
Thank you for agreeing to give me a second chance.
那就一步步来
Baby steps then.
一步步来
Baby steps.
我看到娜莎了
I have eyes on Nyssa.
七街和卢卡街交叉口的一栋废弃大楼里
Abandoned complex at 7th and Rucka.
通知在星城的所有手下
Put the word out among our assets in Star City.
找到厄尔·萨赫尔的人会得到丰厚奖赏
Whoever leads us to Al Sa-Her will be rewarded handsomely.
拖住她  我们马上就到
Keep her there. We're on our way.
娜莎  站住
Nyssa, stop!
-让开  劳蕾尔  -不
- Step aside, Laurel. - No.
休想在我的城市兴风作浪
I will not let you wage your war in my city.
我好意跟你谈判过
I bargained in good faith.
我只是要结束他引起的一切
I'm only finishing what he started,
而且我会迅速了解此事
and I aim to end it swiftly.
可代价是什么
At what cost?
为达目的你不惜牺牲多少生命
How many lives will you sacrifice for what?
我再说一次
I will only say this once more.
闪开
Step aside.
不  你得跟我走
No. You're coming with me.
是吗
Am I?
有人攻击我们
We're under attack!
我们得离开这儿
We have to get out of here.
快跑
Run!
星城中转站
快走  到里面去
Go! Get inside.
跟他们的头儿一样懦弱
Cowards just like their master.
对不住了  娜莎
Sorry, Nyssa.
为什么
For what?
为这一枪
For that.
一年前我也被关在和这很像的笼子里
I was in a cell much like this one barely a year ago.
娜莎  圣莲在哪儿
Nyssa, where is the Lotus?
安全之地
Safe.
这可不是儿戏  娜莎
This isn't a game, Nyssa.
西娅和无辜的平民也都不行了
Thea is dying, innocent civilians are dying,
你自己的人也快撑不住了
Your own men are dying.
就算我现在收手
And surrendering my only leverage
也救不了他们的命
will not save their lives.
但至少能救西娅
No, but it will save Thea's.
你怎么可以这么自私
How could you be so selfish?
这个问题你该去问马尔科姆·梅林
A question better put to Malcolm Merlyn.
他没有解药  但你有
He doesn't have the cure, you do.
用西娅的生命当作谈判筹码
Using Thea's life as a bargaining chip,
为一个注定的败局而见死不救
letting people die for a lost cause--
娜莎  这不是真正的你
Nyssa, this isn't who you are.
这是你父亲的作风
It's who your father was,
但他不在了  他死了
but he's gone, he's dead,
你也终于解脱了
and you can finally be free.
有新发现吗
Any luck?
马尔科姆和联盟彻底消失
Malcolm and the League have gone to ground,
娜莎不肯透露半点消息
Nyssa is a brick wall,
约翰和劳蕾尔出去找圣莲了
John and Laurel are out searching for the Lotus,
但所有地方都快找完了
but we are running out of places to look.
好吧  这可不妙
Well, that's depressing.
我们会找到的  必须找到
Well, we will find it. We have to.
一切都还好吗
Is everything all right?
不太好
Not really.
我是说  没有你妹妹
I mean, it's not as bad as your sister being
昏迷在地下室糟糕  但是
unconscious in our sublevel, but...
你父亲出什么事了吗
Did something happen with your dad?
更像是没出什么事
More like something didn't happen.
那是什么
What's that?
这是特别先进的一款
It's an IR burst receiver,
红外突发接收器
incredibly advanced.
它能从任何房间
It can suck the data out of any room
获取数据
you put it into.
不过别担心  在把它来带之前
Don't worry. I turned it off
我就关掉了
before bringing it down here.
-这不是你的吗  -是我爸的
- It's not yours? - It's my father's.
我带他参观了一下柯蒂斯的研发部
I gave him a little tour of Curtis' R&D lab,
然后他就留下这个当作纪念品
and he left this behind as a souvenir.
他想从帕尔默科技偷取信息
He's trying to steal from Palmer Tech?
实际上只有你这么想
It was your idea actually.
你想弄明白圣莲的作用
You needed proof about the Lotus,
而我想搞懂我爸在干什么
I needed proof about my dad.
所以你设下圈套来考验他
You set a trap for him as a test.
自由出入帕尔默科技的研发实验室
Unrestricted access to Palmer Technologies' R&D lab.
他显然没有通过考验
He flunked with flying colors.
我都不知道自己为何还会吃惊
I don't even know why I'm surprised.
你吃惊是因为你还希望
You're surprised because you're hoping
他是你一直期待的那个父亲
that he's the parent you've always wanted him to be,
能配得上你的父亲
the parent you deserve.
希望他有所改变实在太讽刺了
In an extremely ironic role reversal,
我妈妈就比我聪明
my mother was smarter than me.
她曾说过  "人是不会变的
She said, "People don't change,
即使你希望他们有所改变"
no matter how much you want them to."
只是有些人罢了
Some people don't.
我愿意相信
I'd like to think that there's hope
我们其他人还有希望
for the rest of us,
至少在马尔科姆一事上我有希望
or I did as far as Malcolm is concerned.
约翰觉得我应该杀了他
John thinks I should kill him.
如果这样能救西娅  我也同意
If it'd help save Thea, I agree.
如果他不是西娅的父亲我也会同意
Yeah, and I'd agree if he wasn't Thea's father,
但他是
but he is.
就是因为他我们才卷进了这乱摊子
We are in this mess because of him
无论从哪种角度来看都是这样
on, like, a million different levels.
我们就别假装他们是
Let's not pretend that this is a typical
普通的父女关系了
father-daughter relationship.
他给她洗脑让她去杀朋友
He brainwashed her into killing a friend.
这些我都懂  真的
I know all this. I do,
但是我仍然抱有希望
and I'm still holding out hope
随着时间流逝
that with--with-- with time
每一次他说有多爱她
and with how much he says that he loves her.
也许他们还有可能
That maybe they have some chance
有一点正常的父女之情
at some type of normal relationship.
如果我杀了他
If I kill him...
我妹妹就不会有机会了
my sister never gets that chance.
西娅的父亲比我父亲更不可能改变
Thea's father is no more likely to change than mine is.
又怎么了
What now?
-找到马尔科姆了  -在哪
- Found Malcolm. - Where?
就在我们正下方
Right underneath us.
马尔科姆
Malcolm!
圣莲的作用正在减弱
The Lotus effect is wearing off.
天亮前她就会死去
She will pass by sunrise.
我想陪在她身边
I would like to be by her side.
这该结束了
This has to end.
别再玩花样了
No more games.
你把那该死的戒指交给娜莎
You give Nyssa the damn ring!
我们初次相见时她才四个月大
She was 4 months old when we first met.
你们的管家蕾莎
Your housekeeper Raisa, I believe,
正把你们从我家接走
was picking you up from our house
西娅那时还在婴儿车里
with Thea in a stroller.
我把头偷偷伸进摇篮里看
I peeked my head into the bassinette,
而只有十六周大的西娅
and Thea, all of 16 weeks,
她冲我吐了吐舌头
she stuck her tongue out at me.
我一直知道我们有某种关联
I always knew I was connected to her,
就好像在心底某个地方
as if on some primal level
我知道我是她的父亲
I knew I was her father.
一个称职的父亲是不会为了自己夺权
A real father wouldn't let their child die
让他的孩子白白死掉的
just to keep his hands on power!
我并没有要这么做
That is not what I am doing.
现在正慢慢呈现出来的事情
What's unfolding here is larger than I,
已经远远超越了我和我女儿
and it is bigger than my daughter.
不仅是她生死未定  奥利弗
It's not just her life that hangs in the balance, Oliver.
你和刺客联盟打了这么多次交道
For all your dealings with the League,
却仍然无视它为这世界
you still remain ignorant to what it is
做了什么
they do for the world.
别再说什么刺客联盟了
Enough about the League.
你们不过是一群刺客罢了
You're a group of assassins.
它是一股改变的力量
It is a force of change
几百年来一直
silently manipulating global events
默默控制着全球事件
for hundreds of years.
我不能  也不会把这股力量
And I cannot, I will not put
交到娜莎·厄尔·高福的手里
that kind of power into Nyssa Al Ghul's hands!
我来问你
Let me ask you something.
如果达米恩·达克来找你
If Damien Darhk came to you and told you
让你放下弓  任他完成对星城的计划
to lay down your bow, let him finish his plan for Star City.
你会这么做吗
Would you do it?
即便那意味着能拯救威廉
Even if it meant saving William's life?
我对你了如指掌  奥利弗
I know everything about you, Oliver.
我可是拉斯·厄尔·高福
I am Ra's Al Ghul.
不过说回眼前这个问题
But back to the matter at hand,
你永远不会牺牲这座城市来救你的儿子
you will never sacrifice your city to save your son.
相信我告诉你的
And believe me when I tell you
我不过是和你做了同样的选择
that I am only making the same choice.
不  我会去找另外的办法
No. I would look for another choice,
我会不停地找
and I wouldn't stop looking
直到找到第三条解决之道
until there was a third option!
马尔科姆  如果
Malcolm, what if--
如果你既能得到圣莲
what if you could have the Lotus
又不用交出戒指  如何
and keep your ring?
那是不可能的
I don't see how.
虽不愿承认  但娜莎的力量强得多
Nyssa's forces are stronger than I care to admit.
但她本身并不强大
Not by herself.
你用比武审判
You challenge her
激发了她
to a trial by combat.
你明白这个计划只会要了她的命
You do realize your plan would end in her death?
我们已无路可走了  马尔科姆
We're all backed into a corner, Malcolm.
这是娜莎自己的选择
Nyssa made her bed.
这是你最疯狂的主意之一了
This is one of your crazier ideas,
而你疯狂的主意可不少
and that is a competitive field.
那等着看  我还有一个更疯狂的
Well, sit tight. I have a crazier one coming.
为了得体
In deference to good taste,
我们就不必脱掉上衣了
we will forego the removal of shirts.
那就出招见分晓吧
Let us be finished with this charade.
如你所愿
As you wish.
等一下
Hold!
在刺客联盟的眼中
In the eyes of the League,
这位女士是我的妻子
this woman is my wife.
作为你的丈夫
As your husband,
我愿替她出战
I wish to fight on her behalf.
我绝对不会让任何人替我出战
I have never allowed anyone to fight my battles for me.
你想成为拉斯
Do you want to become Ra's,
还是想送命
or do you want to die?
你为什么要这么做
Why are you doing this?
你告诉过我你打不赢梅林
You told me yourself you couldn't defeat Merlyn,
如果要我在你和他的
and if I am forced to choose
性命之间做出选择
between your life and his...
那我只能伸张正义了
then I will see justice done.
我得说我有点小失望
I'm a little disappointed I must say.
是你把我们逼到这种境地的  马尔科姆
You're the one who put us in this position, Malcolm.
要我提醒你是怎么帮我
Can I remind you the role you played
戴上这枚戒指的吗
in putting this ring on my finger?
不用  我没忘
Oh, I remember.
今晚我要纠正错误
Tonight I correct that mistake.
我不敢相信
I can't believe it.
你经验越足却更加愚蠢了
You've grown even more foolish with experience.
三年了
3 years!
我们来个了结吧
Let's finish this.
最后机会  马尔科姆  投降吧
Last chance, Malcolm. Yield!
绝不投降
Never.
你想了结
To end this,
就必须杀死我
you must kill me.
你一直都知道的  奥利弗
But you always knew that, Oliver.
我不想以这种方式了结
I didn't want it to end this way.
不要虚情假意同情我
Spare me the false sympathy.
动手吧
Just do it.
把圣莲交给我
Bring me the Lotus.
你是拉斯·厄尔·高福
You are Ra's Al Ghul.
谢谢你  丈夫
Thank you, husband.
怎么了
What--what is going on?
没出什么事吧
Is everything ok?
不好说
That, uh, depends.
你感觉怎么样
How are you feeling?
我感觉有点累  可是
I'm--ahem--I'm a bit tired, but--
我为什么会在这里
what am I doing here?
说来话长  长话短说的话
It's a long story, but to shorthand it--
就是你没事了
Is that you're gonna be fine.
你被治愈了  不会再嗜血了
The cure worked. No more bloodlust.
来吧  带你去换上正常的衣服
Come on. Let's go get you into some regular clothes.
奥利弗  你做到了
Oliver, you did it, man.
西娅没事了
Thea's fine,
娜莎和梅林都不用死
and Nyssa and Merlyn didn't have to die.
我不想扫兴
Not to be the buzzkill,
但什么时候才告诉西娅  马尔科姆....
but when are we gonna tell Thea about Malcolm's...
一步步来
Baby steps.
-好吧  -怎么了
- Right. - What's up?
想起了我爸说过的话
Something my father said.
帕尔默科技
给你买了个便携式坡道
Brought you a portable ramp,
你要过高低处时
so anytime you come across a higher surface,
就打开来用
just unfold it.
这会让你畅行无阻
This will get you over almost anything.
我待会儿要去开会
Look. I have a meeting in a few.
我想跟你道别
I just wanted to say good-bye.
道别
Good-bye?
我们才刚开始了解对方
We're just starting to get to know each other.
我已经对你足够了解了
I think I know everything I need to know.
费利西蒂  怎么了
Felicity, what is going on?
我以为我们相处得很顺利
I--I thought we were making progress.
小的时候  我讨厌我自己
When I was a girl, I hated myself.
我以为我是破娃娃  永远都不会
I thought I was broken, that no one could
有人爱我
or ever would love me.
被父亲遗弃的孩子
It's the only way a child can grow up
只能以这种方式长大
when their father abandons them.
费利西蒂
Felicity--
我只想知道为什么
All I ever wanted to know was why.
你为什么要遗弃我  我到底哪里不好
What was so wrong with me that you would leave?
你很好  亲爱的
There was nothing with you, sweetheart.
错在我身上
There was everything wrong with me.
警方  联调局  一直对我
The police, the FBI, they were never going to
穷追不舍
stop looking for me.
我意识到我不该
I realized a life on the run,
让我的妻女
that wasn't the life that I owed you
过逃亡的生活
or your mother,
所以我决定人间蒸发
so I disappeared.
你以为你这么做是为我们好
You thought you were doing the right thing for us.
没错
Exactly.
我这一生都在等的解释
I have waited my entire life for that explanation,
结果我甚至不敢相信答案就是这样
and the thing is I don't even know if I believe it.
这是真相
It's the truth.
你说的话中我只能确认有一部分属实
There is only one part of your story that I know to be true,
那就是警方要逮捕你
and that is that you are wanted by the police.
费利西蒂
Felicity--
我只想让你知道一件事
I just need you to know one thing.
你搞错了
You are wrong.
我跟你完全不同
I am nothing like you.
费利西蒂
Felicity.
诺亚·库特勒  你被捕了
Noah Kuttler, you're under arrest.
你有权保持缄默
You have the right to remain silent.
-你所说的话  -费利西蒂  不行
- Anything you say can... - Felicity, no.
将作为呈堂证供
And will be used against you in a court of law.
不行  你不能这么做
Don't do-- don't do this.
感谢你俩能够过来
Thank you both for coming.
西娅怎样了
How is Thea?
别假装关心她
Don't pretend like you care.
我关心她  她是我的小姑
I do. She's my sister-in-law,
而且她是被我父亲刺伤的
and her condition is the result of my father's blade.
你说得对
You were right.
就算我父亲过世了  我还是他的囚徒
Even after his death, I remained my father's prisoner.
你让我明白了我不用变成
I allowed him to turn me into someone
他要把我变成的人
you showed me I don't have to be...
而你拿剑救我性命的那一刻
And you showed me, as well, when you took up the sword
我就明白了
to save my life.
你俩都让我明白了我该有的决心
You both showed me what needed to be done.
什么决心
And what's that?
耐心点  还有一个人没来
Patience, please. We're waiting for one other.
感谢你能过来  厄尔·萨赫
Thank you for coming, Al Sa-Her.
你是拉斯  我别无选择
You're Ra's. I had no choice.
那么你又搞错了
And so you are mistaken once again.
你在干什么
What are you doing?
今天早上  我把刺客联盟解散了
Earlier today, I disbanded the League of Assassins.
我像我父亲很久以前
I released its forces
释放你那样  释放他们
much as my father had released you long ago.
大家都不再是我父亲的囚徒了
No one will be held prisoner by my father any longer.
我曾经把你视为儿子  奥利弗
I thought of you as a son once, Oliver.
你比我的孩子更像我
I had more in common with you than my own blood,
但我不会因此而不杀你
but that's not the reason why I'm not going to kill you.
也不是因为
Neither the fact
你是我女儿的哥哥
that you are my daughter's brother.
我让你活着是因为
The reason you get to live
如果把你杀死
is because death would be a mercy compared
就太便宜你了
to the debt I now owe you.
你威胁不了我  马尔科姆
Don't you dare threaten me, Malcolm.
泰安娜
Taiana.
我答应你为了瓦勒徳我会释放你的朋友
I promise I will free your friends for Vlad.
瓦勒徳已经死了
Vlad is dead.
我们是为他们而做的
We do this for them.
奎恩先生
Mr. Queen.
我希望你已经恢复力气了
I hope you have regained your strength.
你给我的石头是这个最终地图的
The stone you gave me was the final piece of the puzzle,
最后一块拼图
the final map.
-我们要去挖掘  -你说什么
- We are going to dig. - Dig?
我要找的天堂不在天上
The heaven I seek is not above
而是在我们的脚下
but rather beneath our feet.
我们天亮就去挖掘
We dig at daybreak.
你好点了吗
You feeling any better?
我不知道为什么自己会那么伤心
I don't even know why I'm so upset.
不是所有期待已久的父女团聚
Doesn't every long-awaited father-daughter reunion end
都会以爸爸被铐走收场吗
with the dad being taken away in handcuffs.
你不用为我强颜欢笑
You don't have to be funny for me.
你知道的吧
You know that, right?
我知道
I know.
而且我知道我做得对  但...
And I know I did the right thing, but...
当发现是我举报他时
the look on his face when he realized
他脸上的表情
I had turned him in,
我将会永生难忘
it's gonna haunt me for the rest of my life,
我甚至觉得
and I can't help but think he doesn't
他不该被同情
even deserve that kind of remorse.
我认为你同情他
I think that remorse is a pretty clear indicator
表示你跟他完全不同
that you are a very different person than him.
也许我跟西娅该去做T恤
Maybe Thea and I could make t-shirts.
去参加俱乐部
We could join a club.
听我说  不要误认为
Listen to me. Don't make the mistake
你跟你爸爸的事已经结束了
of thinking that this thing with your dad is over.
从我的经验看来
I can tell you from experience
这种事没有这么容易了结
that closure does not come that easily.
说到了结
Speaking of closure,
你在惩罚自己背叛马尔科姆吗
are you punishing yourself for betraying Malcolm?
-这样很疯狂吗  -是的
- Is that insane? - Yes,
不过这就是我爱的你
but it's part of what makes you the man I love.
约翰说得对
John was right.
你面对绝境
You were faced with an impossible situation,
找到了最好的抽身方式
and you found the best way out of it.
你愿意嫁给我吗
Will you marry me?
我想我已经给你答案了
I think I already answered that question.
西娅和安迪都没事了
Thea's better, Andy's better,
达克那边也很平静
things are quiet on the Darhk front.
我感觉现在就是我们的时机
I feel like this might be our window,
我们在过去几个月经历了
and with everything that we have gone through
那么多事  我要你告诉我
over the past few months, I want you to tell me
我们还在等什么
why are we waiting?
好吧  我们要计划一下
Well, we'll have to plan it.
也许搞个小型仪式
Maybe just a small ceremony
邀请几个朋友  不设宴
with a few of our friends and no caterers.
我妈一定不高兴
My mom will hate that.
我同意
I'm in.
我不喜欢等人
I don't like to be kept waiting.
我很抱歉
My apologies.
我已经没有以前那些资源了
I don't have the resources I once had.
我知道你的人生最近发生转变了
Yes. I'm aware of your recent reversal of fortune.
你才因此要求见面的吧
I take it that's why you asked for this meeting.
我不会空手而来的
Well, I haven't come empty-handed.
那就说吧
So to speak.
我有你可能会特别感兴趣的信息
I have some information that you might find of particular interest.
我知道奥利弗·奎恩在这世上最在乎谁
I know who Oliver Queen cares about more than anyone in the whole world.
我也知道
Yeah, so do I.
我们已经对付过她了
We did a pretty good number on her over the holidays.
那个人不是费利西蒂·斯莫克
It's not Felicity Smoak.
是谁
Who?
他儿子
His son...
威廉
William.